You are not as far away from profitable
trading as you may think. There is a
massive amount of information pulling
you in all different directions. So your
confusion is warranted and understood.
But the truth is there are only a few
very specific skills that it takes to
have a profitable trading career. And in
this video, I'm going to be sharing with
you three technical analysis secrets
that I can guarantee will improve your
trading and help you master the three
skills it takes to become a [music]
professional trader.
Welcome back. Just in case you're brand
new, my name is Stephen. I've been
trading for about a decade. And on this
channel, I try to share all the
expertise and skills that I've acquired
over the past decade of my own trading
career to you to help speed up your
journey to profitable trading. Now,
let's go ahead and get started with
secret number one. Secret number one is
that technical analysis by itself does
not work. Don't get me wrong, there is a
place for technical analysis in trading.
Technical analysis is even necessary to
become a profitable trader. But
technical analysis by itself does not
work. Now, I know what you're thinking.
If that's the case, then why would I
even learn it? I'm going to get into
that in just a second. First though, let
me give you an analogy to help you
understand what I mean.
Technical analysis is like knowing how
to play blackjack. You can know how to
play blackjack really well. You can know
every rule to the game. And yet, even
though you know every rule to the game,
you can walk into the casino and lose
money at the blackjack table. Now,
imagine you knew how to count cards.
Counting cards is just a strategy that
players use in order to create a
mathematical edge over the casino. It's
the strategy players use to have a
statistic advantage that ends up making
them money over time. If you just know
technical analysis, that's like knowing
the rules to blackjack. You can know the
rules to the market, but you can still
fail as a trader. And just like in
blackjack, players create a strategy
that gives them a mathematical statistic
edge over the casino. In trading, we
create a strategy using different
technical factors that we repeat over
and over and that gives us an edge over
the market that gives us a money-making
statistic advantage over time. But the
next question is if we need a strategy
based around technical factors, then how
do we create a strategy? I have a very
specific way that I create trading
strategies. But before I show you that,
I want you to keep in mind that all
technical factors are not created equal.
So, just a little foreshadowing here. By
the end of this video, you're going to
know the four technical factors that
I've seen work the best throughout my
decade of trading experience. So, make
sure to stick around for secret number
two. Let's go and talk about how I build
strategies, though. The first step for
me building a strategy is to create what
I call conditions. Conditions are going
to be technical factors that align
before you look for an entry reason.
These could be things like market in
trend, market at a moving average,
market oversold, divergence on an RSI
indicator. It could be things like the
market just created a double bottom. All
those would be conditions before I look
for an entry reason. So, every strategy
that I've ever created, every strategy
that I use starts with me analyzing the
market and finding the conditions that
meet the criteria of the strategy that
I'm trading. And by the way, this is all
part of an acronym I use to create
strategies that I call CEST. CEST stands
for conditions and E stands for entry
reason. So, after we have our conditions
met, the next thing we're going to do is
start looking for an actual reason to
enter. The problem that most traders
have is that even if they have a
strategy, they don't know exactly when
they're going to press the buy or sell
button depending on if they're going
long or short. So because of that, they
get confused even if they have a good
set of conditions on when they're going
to place the trade. So for that reason,
you want an exact rule for when you're
going to place the trade. Is it based on
a candlestick pattern? Is it based on a
few different candlestick patterns you
use? Is it based on a chart pattern? Is
it based on a limit order based on
Fibonacci? What is your actual reason
for entry? You must have a rule for that
in a rules-based strategy in order to
stay consistent to it. In CES ST or
CEST, the S stands for your stop-loss.
In every trading strategy I've ever
used, I have a place where I know I'm
wrong and I'm going to get out of the
market if I know I'm wrong. So, if the
reason I initially entered the trade no
longer looks to be valid, then I have my
stop loss set in an appropriate place,
which might be above or below structure,
above or below a swing high or low,
above or below a candlestick in order to
ensure that I get out when the market's
showing me it's not aligning with the
initial analysis that I did. You're
going to lose trades at times, and when
you do, you want to make sure you have a
plan in place so you're not just
guessing at when you're supposed to get
out of the market. that can lead to
losses that are much higher than you
really want them to be and eventually
could possibly lead to you blowing your
entire account. So stop loss is what the
S stands for and in c it stands for
conditions entry stop and did you guess
target? Target is the next one. We need
a place where we get out if we find out
that we're wrong in our analysis. Well,
we also need at least an idea of where
we're going to be getting out if we're
correct. What if we're right? Where am I
going to take profit? Is it going to be
based on this level of resistance? Is it
going to be based just on a specific
reward to risk ratio? These are all
things that you need to consider when
creating a strategy. And what you just
learned is the exact process that I use
when creating a strategy. I create
conditions. I create an entry reason. I
create a rule for my stop-loss and a
rule for my target. And that together
equals a rules-based strategy like
counting cards in blackjack, which gives
me an edge over the market over a long
period of time. Now, secret number two.
Here, I'm going to share with you my
four favorite technical factors. Now,
you just learned about Ces. What we're
going to do is combine all four of these
technical factors in order to create a
strategy just like counting cards is a
strategy for winning at blackjack. This
strategy is going to be what gives us a
money-making edge over the market. Now,
just keep in mind that these are just
the best technical factors from my
experience. Depending on your trading
style, you're more than welcome to have
more than four, to have completely
different technical factors than me, but
from my experience, these are the
technical factors that work best. And
they are number one, trend, number two,
major levels of structure, number three
chart patterns, and number four
candlestick patterns. Now, what we're
going to do is go look at these on a
chart. We're actually going to build an
entire strategy based around those four
technical factors. And we're going to
use CS
in order to do that. All right. So,
let's build a strategy together using CS
and the four technical factors that I
just told you were my favorites and the
ones I've seen work best throughout my
decade of trading experience. Number one
on the list of technical factors for
conditions for me is going to be trend.
I'm going to look for trend when trading
this specific strategy every single
time. Now, a trend is normally very easy
to spot. And if it's not easy to spot,
if something's in trend, then it's not
in trend. So, that's how you can tell.
If it's getting difficult to figure out
if something's in an uptrend, a
downtrend, or consolidating, it's more
than likely just consolidating. So, for
trend, we're looking for price to have
made a lower low compared to the
previous low. And as long as that has
happened, as long as we have a close
below this low, I consider a market in
trend. I also like to use a moving
average just to give me a better idea of
that. The moving average of my choice is
the 50 EMA. So for condition number one
for me, I would want to see price below
the 50 EMA and price creating a new
lower low. So that would be condition
number one. I'm going to have multiple
conditions for this specific strategy.
I'll also end up with multiple entry
reasons. You'll figure that out in just
a second. But condition number two for
me after trend is going to be a major
level of structure. Now, I identify
major levels of structure in a very
specific way. The major level of
structure for me needs to be the latest
level that was broken in this downtrend,
which is right here. And it must be a
level that's been tested multiple times.
So, here we have one test of support,
one test of support. That's already two.
But if I scroll left, you can see that
price also reacted from this level as
support multiple times yet again looking
left. So, this is what would qualify for
me as a major structure level. actually
call these OTZs or optimal trading
zones. So, condition one, we need to see
price and trend. What does that mean?
We're below the 50 EMA and we've just
made a new lower low compared to the
most recent low. If that's the case, we
have condition one met. Condition number
two, we need a pullback into what I
consider a major level of structure or
OTZ. The rules for this is it's the
latest level that was broken and it's
been tested multiple times. Once I have
those conditions met, I'm actually ready
to start looking for an entry reason.
Now, the two types of entry reasons that
I personally use for strategies like
this are I like to use chart patterns or
candlestick patterns. A candlestick
pattern would be more of an aggressive
move depending on other market factors.
If I want to be a little more
aggressive, then I may just use a
candlestick pattern. And a chart pattern
would be a more conservative move where
I don't want to be quite as aggressive
on that specific trade. Now, on this
trade specifically, we were looking at
this as a candlestick pattern. If you
look with me right here, you'll see that
we get this engulfing candle. Price has
since pushed lower. This is a live trade
on a live account. You can see that
right down here. And also, just so you
know, this is a trade I sent out to
every member of the TTC Forex
University, which is our flagship
course. They get email analysis like
this two to five times per week. Not all
of them win, obviously, but they do get
these emails, including my entry, stops,
and targets for these types of trades.
If you're interested in learning more
about that, click the top link in the
description or go to
www.tcfxuniversity.com.
If not, that's completely fine. Let's
continue with the video. So, entry
reason in this case was this engulfing
candle. We have an engulfing candle
directly after a dogey candle which told
me selling pressure after all of my
conditions were already met. So, to
break this strategy down completely, we
had trend below 50 EMA making new lower
lows. We had major structure, previous
level of support that was broken, tested
multiple times. After that, we have our
conditions met. So C is done. After C,
what am I looking for? E, I'm looking
for an entry. So these are my two
choices for entry. Candlestick patterns
for more aggressive trades or chart
patterns for a more conservative
approach. In this case, we went with a
candlestick pattern in this engulfing
bar we just pointed out. Now, am I done
creating a strategy? No. Hopefully, you
caught that. We still need to discuss
stops and targets. So, let's do that.
Now, for stops on this specific trade
and with this specific strategy, I like
to do about one times the ATR indicator.
And that might sound complicated. It's
just an indicator that you can find on
Trading View that gives you the average
of the last 14 candles, the average size
of them, so you can kind of stay in line
with the volatility of the market when
you're placing a stop-loss, which is
exactly what I did here. So, I normally
go one times this little indicator,
which right now, if you look at my top
left, it's 26 pips. So, I went 26 pips
above the high of this engulfing candle,
which was the swing high of the
pullback. That was my stop loss. So, now
I have C E S and I need T for a target.
I've already taken off the first part of
my position, but I wanted to hold the
second part of my position until we got
to the next major structure level.
Again, that's a technical factor I use
all the time for taking targets, for
setting stop losses, for placing entries
is levels of structure that have been
tested multiple times. So that's where
my second target is and that's going to
give me if it gets hit around a 1.8 to1
on the second part of the position.
Let's recap really quickly everything.
We have C conditions trend and at a
major level of structure as I've defined
it. We have E for an entry reason which
is going to be either sharp patterns for
a conservative approach or candlestick
patterns for a more aggressive approach.
Then we have S which stands for our
stop-loss and for me that's going to be
one ATR above the entry candle. Then we
have T which stands for targets which is
going to be at the next major level of
structure price is going to hit if it
goes in my direction. So this is my
version of counting cards against the
market. Pretty solid stuff, right? Go
ahead and click that like button for me
if you enjoyed the video so far. And now
let me actually take you down to the
15-minute chart because in this case I
can give you a bonus technical factor
that I love to use. So let's do this
again on the 15-minute chart. But on
this chart we're looking at this as more
of a reversal. We did actually get a
double top here. So again, chart
patterns. Here's my double top. And what
I want to show you on this chart though
is a bonus technical factor. And that
bonus technical factor is RSI
divergence. Whenever I see RSI
divergence, it is another technical
factor that I will consider using for an
extra condition with a strategy. And it
was one of the reasons we did a more
aggressive approach on the specific
trade. If we look here, we have the
highs of price consistently heading in
which direction? Up or down? They're
going higher, right? Well, if we look at
the RSI indicator, what are the highs of
the RSI indicator doing? They're
consistently getting lower. This is what
we call divergence and it could be
another hint of a reversal. It can
stand, at least for me, as a bonus
condition. So, keep all that in mind and
let's move on now to the last technical
analysis secret. Secret number three is
that technical analysis will never fix
your mindset. No matter how good you get
at technical analysis, no matter how
good you are at analyzing a chart,
knowing technical analysis will never
fix that space that's right above your
eyes where hopefully your brain is right
between your ears. The mindset you have
when you're trading, your discipline,
your ability to stay disciplined to a
strategy, stay disciplined to a risk
management plan, your ability to keep
from switching strategies, to keep from
moving your stops and targets. Your
mindset around trading will never be
fixed with technical analysis. But
here's what will fix it. Good trading
psychology and a good trading mindset is
not something you're just born with.
It's not something that comes natural,
but it's something that you can learn.
And if you want to be a profitable
trader, it's something you must learn.
Every single profitable trader,
including myself, at some point was
losing money due to having bad trading
psychology. And eventually they made the
realization that trading psychology is
just as or more important than the
strategy that you trade. They flipped
the switch, got better at trading
psychology, improved their trading
mindset, and then became profitable
traders. That's the journey nearly every
profitable trader goes on, and it's the
journey that you're on right now. Let me
give you a short story. It won't take
long. When I first started trading, my
trading psychology was absolute It
was so bad that I was consistently
switching strategies from one to the
other on almost a daily or at best
weekly basis. I never stuck to any of
the rules I had in place, including
where my stop loss was supposed to go.
If I started losing a trade, I would
just keep moving my stop loss down
because I was terrified of actually
losing money because I had a bad trading
mindset. I also would move my target up
if I thought the market would keep
going. But what does that even mean? I
thought the market would keep going.
That's called trading based on emotions.
And that's not what you do if you want
to be a profitable trader. And I also
caught myself consistently trading not
based on the strategy or the plan that I
had in place, but trading based off
solely fear and greed. If I was really
greedy that day, I would try to buy
seven, eight, nine times throughout the
day with no entry reason. If I was
really scared that day, I would just
skip trades that actually met all the
rules of my plan. So, trading based on
emotions is what caused so many losses
for me, what caused me to blow my first
account, nearly blow the second one. And
all of those mistakes are what I hope to
help you avoid with these three hacks.
So, with that being the case, let's go
ahead and get started with hack number
one. So, the first trading psychology
tip that literally saved my trading
account was that I needed to manage my
expectations. And at the time, I didn't
understand what trading was. When I
first started trading, I saw trading as
a way to get rich overnight, like many
of you probably did at first as well.
And eventually, reality sets in and you
realize, "Oh this is a lot harder
than the guru or whoever said it was
going to be. This is a lot harder even
than I expected it to be." And instead
of making money and getting rich like I
thought I was going to, I'm just
consistently watch my savings account
dwindle as I add money to a trading
account and lose it time and time again.
That's the realization I had. And what
that did for me is helped me to realize
that trading isn't some kind of
get-richquick scheme. Trading is a way
to build wealth over time. And it can
help you become wealthy. It can, but not
as fast as most people think it can. So
understanding what trading is, which is
a way to get wealthy over a long period
of time, not a way to get rich super
fast. and managing your expectations by
saying, "Okay, it is really, really,
really unlikely and nearly impossible
for me to be making 100% a week, 100% a
month would be wildly nearly impossible.
100% a year. Now, we're getting closer
to something that's doable. And it all
really depends on a ton of different
factors, like the time frame you're
trading, the strategy you're using.
There could be situations where you make
more than 100% a year. There could be a
lot of situations where you make less.
But managing your expectations and
getting away from expecting to get rich
within 12 months just from trading, that
is a very unlikely scenario. So, I
wanted to step in real quick to talk a
little more about trading expectations.
As I said, it's impossible for me to
know what you should expect out of your
trading because it's based on an
infinite number of factors. There's
literally no way for me to know or to
tell you what you should expect. The
reason I said 100% a year is doable is
because that's what I've come to expect
based on my own experience. As you can
see on the screen, this is my FX book, a
thirdparty verifier that verifies, track
records, and verifies your trading
results. This is my account, my real
account. And this is my results over the
past about 8 months of 2023. As you can
see, we have about a 61% return. And if
we do the math on that, 61% divided by,
it's not quite 8 months, but we'll go 8
months is 7.6% per month. If I multiply
that by 12 and if everything continues
as planned, I'll make about 91% this
year. So that's why I'm telling you that
at least based on my experience, my
expectations have come out to around
100% a year in my own trading. So in
conclusion, to help out with your
trading mindset, remember that trading
is a long game. Learning how to trade is
going to take a long time. And then
becoming consistently profitable with a
large account is when you're going to
make money. becoming consistently
profitable with a small account, you
will make money, but it's going to be a
smaller amount of money. And that's
okay. That's supposed to happen. That's
exactly what I went through. And
eventually, I was able to build that
small account into a multiple six-figure
account that I trade now. So, don't be
frustrated hearing that. Just understand
that that's the reality of trading. Tip
number two that drastically improved my
trading psychology was back testing my
trading strategy in order to increase
belief. If you're trading a system or a
strategy, or god forbid, you're just
trading without a system and placing buy
and sell orders based on emotions like I
did at the beginning of my career, you
definitely got to stop doing that. But
if you're trading just based on strategy
you've never tested, you're just
believing what somebody else said that
taught it to you or you're just placing
trades based on what you think may work
and you've never tested it in historic
data, you're going to have a really hard
time sticking to that strategy. It's
going to be nearly impossible for you to
go through any type of losing streak
without trying to switch to another
strategy and getting shiny object
syndrome where you're consistently just
looking for the next best thing. What
you must do in order to improve and
increase belief is you must back test
that strategy to see that it's at least
worked in the past. That's going to
increase your belief, which in turn will
increase your discipline and help you
with your mindset, help you with your
trading psychology. The more you believe
in this strategy, the easier it's going
to be for you to handle losses and for
you to handle inevitable drawdowns. When
we're trading, back to number one,
understanding what trading is, we're
trading not based on the fact that we
know what the market's going to do.
We're trading based on a statistic
advantage that we have over a long
period of time by trading a strategy
that we've made or learned that's proven
to give an edge through the back testing
process. And back testing itself is
really simple. Let's say you wanted to
trade, and this is not a strategy I
would suggest, but let's just say you
wanted to trade hammer and shooting star
candles that come off of a moving
average. If that was the case, you would
just take that exact rule set, go back
through historic data, and look for
every time that happened. Every time a
hammer candlestick came off a moving
average, did I win or lose that trade
based on my stops and target. Every time
a shooting star candle came off a moving
average, and we were already in a
downtrend and that happened, did I win
or lose that trade? And what was my
reward to risk ratio? you would go back
and you record all of that information
back in the past for at least 100
instances of that happening. And once
you have done that, then you will see
whether or not that strategy has made
money in the past and therefore whether
or not it's likely to make money in the
future. And again, this is something
that literally saved my trading account
because it helped me to increase my
belief in the strategies I was trading
to the point that I now have mastered my
mindset in terms of trading and hardly
ever make any trading mistakes. I
definitely never switch strategies, move
my stop or move my target because of
emotions anymore. And a lot of that was
because I managed my expectations in
terms of trading. I understand what
trading is and I've backtested all the
strategies that I currently trade and
I've seen them work in the past. I've
seen them go in and out of draw down, in
and out of losing streaks and still come
out on top after a large sample size,
which again does incredible things for
your trading psychology. And the last
trading psychology tip that again
completely saved my trading account was
understanding and managing risk
correctly. So just understanding the
risks involved in trading is the first
part of that. You need to know that
you're going to have losses no matter
how good you get at trading. You could
understand technical analysis like the
back of your hand. You can understand
the strategy you're trading like the
back of your hand and you will still
have losing trades. You will still go
through draw downs. I've been trading
for a decade. I still have draw downs. I
have weeks that I don't make money. I
have weeks that I lose money. That's a
very normal part of trading. And the way
we help to manage our emotions while
we're going through those losing streaks
and sometimes those losing weeks is we
manage our risk correctly. If I go
through a draw down of let's say five
trades in a row and I'm risking 10% of
my account, that's a 50% draw down in my
account. If you had a $100,000 account,
that would be a $50,000 draw down.
That's not something anybody would be
comfortable with. that would be
extremely difficult to manage your
emotions during a draw down like that
after only five trades. So instead of
risking 10% per trade, it's way better
to manage risk correctly. Let me explain
why people risk that much though when
you're first starting out. Again, same
thing that I did. You're looking to make
money as fast as possible. You want to
literally get rich overnight or at least
as fast as you possibly can. And because
of that, the way risk works is the more
you risk on a trade, the more you stand
to make on a trade. But vice versa, the
other side of that coin, the more you
risk on a trade, obviously the more you
could possibly lose as well. So although
when we first come into the market, it
it's really enticing to think about what
could happen if we won 10 trades in a
row with a 10% risk, we could be we
could get rich, but winning 10 trades in
a row without even knowing how to trade
is a very unlikely situation. And the
much more likely thing that will happen
is you'll lose five to seven trades and
you'll be in a massive draw down. you'll
lose a majority of your account because
you're risking 10% per trade or more.
Now, the correct way to do this is to
figure out a number that you would be
comfortable with because it it's not
there's no cookie cutter answer. I can't
tell you exactly what to risk. I have no
idea what your risk tolerance is. And I
don't know how much you're willing to
lose on a specific trade or during a
draw down. You have to decide that
number. But once you have that number
decided, you can start to determine what
you need to risk every time you place a
trade. For me, I risk between 1 and 2%
of my account value. Let's take that
same scenario now. I lose five trades in
a row. Well, if I lose five trades in a
row, which I have before, even now after
a decade of trading, I've lost five
trades in a row recently. When I lose
five trades in a row, I only lose about
10% of my overall account value. So,
that hit is not nearly as hard as it
would be if I was risking way more than
that. So, my emotions still stay under
control, and it keeps me stable. It
keeps me from wanting to switch
strategies, from wanting to change the
strategies that I'm already trading,
from getting super frustrated and
quitting trading for a week. It keeps me
from making emotional mistakes because I
don't have all of my hard-earned money
at risk during one trade. So again, to
recap, manage your expectations and
understand what trading truly is. You're
not going to be making a,000% a week.
telling you what to expect is really
difficult because again it depends on
the strategy you're trading on your
trading style. It depends on the time
frame you're trading. Depends on way too
many factors. But don't be expecting
a,000% a week. Trading is not something
where you you know exactly what the
market's going to do and that's why
you're a profitable trader. Trading is
having statistic advantage that plays
out over time. You'll go through wins
and losses, but if you have a profitable
strategy, then the wins will prevail and
you will have profits in your account
over a long period of time. Number two,
back test your trading strategy. Take
the rules you've created or learned for
a trading strategy and look at them
through historic data for at least 100
trades. No matter how long it takes to
find that 100 trades, you want to do
that so you can prove to yourself that
it's a strategy worth trading. So you
can increase your belief and therefore
increase your trading psychology and
increase your trading mindset. I said
increase, I meant improve your trading
psychology and your trading mindset. So
back testing is number two. Number
three, probably one of the most
important on this list, is to understand
the risks involved in trading and manage
those risks accordingly by applying a
riskmanagement plan that keeps you
comfortable even during losing trades,
that keeps you comfortable even during
periods of draw down, which are
inevitable and will happen. If you do
those three things, I guarantee your
trading psychology will improve
dramatically. Now, if you are someone
who is brand new or struggling to learn
how to trade and you want to know the
exact steps that took me from a
construction worker roofing houses to a
professional trader, then I'm looking
for 500 new or struggling traders right
now to join us in the TTC Forex
University. It's a full mentorship
program that includes a university style
course taking you through all the steps
that I personally took to go from
construction worker to professional
trader. It also comes with the protrader
report and email analysis which are
trades I'm taking throughout the week
that give you a glimpse into how I'm
actually trading in real markets and in
real time. On top of that, you get
priority coaching support through email,
meaning any questions that you have.
It'll be me on the other end answering
those questions for you to ensure you
have the smoothest journey to profitable
trading possible. And on top of all
that, it also comes with a 30-day money
back guarantee. So you have peace of
mind that if you get in the program and
for some reason decide you don't want to
trade forex anymore, no big deal at all.
Just send us an email and we'll get you
refunded ASAP with no questions asked.
If that's something you're interested
in, go ahead and go to
www.ttcfxuniversity.com.
That'll also be on the screen. If not,
that's completely fine, too. So, I hope
you enjoyed this video and I'll see you
in the next